[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello this is Frank defreitis and
welcome to another week of holotalk for
the week of November 1st 1998.
my guest this week is holographic artist
Melissa Crenshaw who will be celebrating
20 years of working with the splendid
light in 1999.
Melissa currently has an exhibit of her
work both past and present at the
gallery located in Artisan Square on
Bowen Island British Columbia
the gallery is open Friday Saturday and
Sunday and the show runs through
November 22nd
Melissa Crenshaw trivia
most holography Publications mention
Canadian artist Melissa Crenshaw but did
you know
she was born in Kansas
here's the holotalk interview with
Melissa it runs about 20 minutes I will
not be back on after the interview so I
will thank you now for tuning in and
hope that you will continue to tune in
to all of the guests that I have coming
on the second season of holotalk here's
Melissa
you've been involved in so many things
you've been involved with holographic
production
curating lecturing writing and education
why don't we just go down that list and
talk about some of those things in order
okay as far as your production I think
some of the listeners might be
interested in your work with multiple
color reflection holography I guess I
started to explore the possibilities of
color back in the early 80s
um I've almost always worked in
reflection mode it's only been this last
year that I started to work in
transmission why reflection other than
white light transmission or one of the
others well in the early days like I
didn't really like the rainbow effect it
just didn't work with the kinds of
images that I was producing the images
that I I was producing needed to
basically maintain their color from any
viewing position oh I see okay and with
the rainbow technique of course you know
as you change your vertical Parallax or
your vertical position
you know the image shifts colors so yeah
that works beautifully for some people's
work but for mine it didn't there was no
reason for that to happen so I started
to work in reflection mode
and in the early days I just tried
experiments using variations in exposure
to shift colors slightly and then I
started working with the triathanolamine
technique swelling technique which I had
to teach myself and um that's rough
isn't it
it's nothing like working on a piece for
a couple days and find out you've got
this Blue Streak going down the middle
oh yeah mini blue streaks there's a lot
of holograms that could have gone into
Edition that ended up going into the
trash because there was a a one inch by
eighth inch Blue Streak on the left side
down by the bottom I mean it's it's
almost painful that that technique but
it was the only way to do colors because
it's the only way to do color unless you
have three lasers and blah blah blah
yeah so I just did it and the early work
I was doing then was I was really
excited about the Russian constructivist
work from the early part of the century
and there was a lot of network being
exhibited and I was actually
exploring geometric shapes in the same
kind of spatial relationships that the
the constructivists were actually
looking at and you know color reflection
holography was a great way to do that
did you work directly with the
reflection hologram itself or to just
shoot Masters first and then do
transfers so in the in in the beginning
back in the early 80s I did a lot of I
did a lot of single beam reflection work
I mean it was easy optically it was the
simplest technique you could do yeah and
I put all of the complication if you
like into the color technique there's
only a few of us that have actually
worked with that very simple Optical
technique and it's too bad because
there's a type of image and there are
things you can do with a single beam
reflection hologram that you really
can't do with a multiple beam so I did
that for a few years and then I started
working multiple beams but still not
using a master yes and then in the mid
80s I started working with Masters how
did you ever manage did you come up with
a special technique that you could let
the listeners know about because I know
a lot of people like to try this
triathanolene okay you can't go through
holography without giving that a shot
how did you come about where you got it
down to the fact that you knew that you
weren't going to get any streaking on
the plate
ever work that out okay but it's very
much trial and errand to get your own
individual technique in terms of the
shooting geometry and the pre-swelling
the best paper is probably the very
early paper by lawn more and grew yeah
from the 1982 International Symposium
papers yes from Lake Forest
um that explains it Steve McGrew then
produced a paper showing a graphical
method whereby you could actually lay
the Optics out on graph paper and know
how to do your angle changes and things
which are critical for color control
that's an excellent paper to explain
that and the rest of it is just trial
and error I mean I basically soaked the
plate and triathanolamine and I would
squeegee the surface of it very
carefully wash the back of the glass let
it just dry for three hours shoot it and
see what happens yeah color mix seems
very tricky but you can um
you know you just keep experimenting
it's it's a it's an RGB color mixing
process so yeah
um very similar to a monitor on the
computer
I guess so yeah is that our GPS yeah
yeah it's light it's light mixing it's
additive colored and then later on
toward the mid to late 80s you were
working with Sydney dinsman oh yeah yes
I Sydney came to me and actually in 1986
I in 85 and 86 boat I worked in China I
worked in Beijing and in 86 I was
directing a very large International
exhibition there and I needed an
assistant curator and I hired Sid they
didn't even know each other at that
point and we ended up sitting in this
little tiny room in China together for
six weeks and came out of it best friend
and she asked me then to do a
collaborative project with her and that
project ended up lasting seven years
and we did we ended up collaborating
um until she moved to Hong Kong she
moved to Hong Kong get married and have
a family so that was a wonderful
collaboration and we produced figurative
Works she had some kind of accountable
grants we were able to go to Germany and
work with Fred undercare and shoot pulse
Masters and we also worked with Hans via
Calvin and Chicago shooting pulse
Masters and we generated a number of
series and we were very successful with
that work we actually made a real living
with that word
as far as you're curating you've also
curated a number of different shows over
the years
here in North America and Canada and
also in Europe I imagine and China
itself didn't you
um mainly the two that were in China and
then in Canada I actually Sydney is was
a curator also and I assisted her on a
couple of shows in particular images in
time and space where I was sort of the
lighting specialist for that very large
exhibition
um I directed The exhibitions in Beijing
two of them a small one and then one in
association with an International
Conference in 86 and then I did the big
1988 Lake Forest International Symposium
exhibition in in Chicago that was a
really big show it was really fun were
you involved with the publication wave
front oh yes
um I did this photography for that that
journal for a few years and then the
last issue which we we call the
recession special was actually produced
by Alvarez and myself and it was a bit
of a spoof everything was so Dreadful
then with the museum closing and the the
market and art crashing we decided we
needed to do something to lives in
people's spirits up so we produced a bit
of a spoof issue and that was really
quite quite fun how many issues take us
away from
oh boy I don't even know maybe there
were 10 or something okay
did the work on wavefront but it did
come out of Vancouver
photography beautiful publication a
beautiful publication oh it's a
wonderful Journal I mean it was you know
it had a real artist slant
um it was very non-commercial and um of
course you know everybody's Pockets got
empty doing it but it was it would be
wonderful to start that up again
especially on on the internet which is
quite possible you know because I was
real involved now and
I don't believe there are any
Publications on holography anymore
either the only one I know of is the
holography business news
that still comes out that's pretty much
aimed at the embossing industry though
but there is no you know but at one time
we had three journals and we don't have
the kind of comprehensive holosphere
um or wave foot Journal now that covers
the whole industry which is a real shame
what about your luxury
um I haven't done any of that in a while
but I was very fortunate in that because
I did a lot of the early color work in
holography people wanted to know about
it and I was brought into lecture at
various places I I did workshops and
lectures again in Beijing that was the
institute for post and
Telecommunications
um I lectured in MIT once I lectured at
the University
we have done various lectures for
Galleries and museums and that's that's
always kind of fun you know you get free
plane tickets yeah do you still do that
travel around
not too much um the last couple of years
I've been working for an engineering
company here that develops platonic
switches I I bought a house I needed to
kind of you know concentrate on you know
earning a living for a while the last
big conference and lecture I did was the
Nottingham conference in England two
years ago
I think that's called The International
Conference on our holography yes yes and
there's actually a site on the web for
that as well yeah
what is it like making your first
hologram why even get involved with that
and how did you get involved with it
um that goes back to what 78.79 79 you
know I was a social worker in the 70s I
lived in Chicago I did a lot of
um I worked for HUD agencies I did a lot
of Street Social Work emergency services
and they took a year off because I got
very burnt out yeah and I thought well
I'll just study film or something right
for fun and then I found out about
holography I had been reading about Carl
Pilgrim's theory on the holographic mine
yes in Stanford neurosurgeon he was a
neurophysiologist yes it had some very
fascinating papers on
using the Hologram as a model for
understanding how the neural networks
and things operate and so I thought well
that's really neat and then I found out
that there was actually a place in
Chicago that taught and displayed real
Holograms so I went there and I
immediately signed up for class that was
Lauren Billings place
um
do you remember who was teaching back
then there John Hoffman okay and it was
an amazing time because in my class I
had Doug Tyler Ed Wesley and Steve Smith
no kidding wow and Tom specovic and
their diet Dietrich had just graduated
with the class before mine so it was a
real hot bit of holography at that time
it was wonderful
taught really good basic techniques so a
lot of people got a good foundation
there I had a feeling you saw your first
time Oh I thought it was incredible I
couldn't believe it I did a little tiny
two inch by two inch laser trench
Mission image of a ribbon curl uh it was
a sand table and the the curled ribbon
went back about 20 inches oh no kidding
wow yeah it was a little late getting
you had to use it I'll use here to see
it yeah I guess he was hooked at that
point apparently I love laser
transmission Holograms I love them
talk about data storage uh I mean I've
got some pulse Masters that
um were shot
um there's one that Michael page shot
for me for a commercial job and you can
see the entire inside of the room where
we shot the master wow it's just
incredible you can see the clock on the
wall like 15 feet away like it's just
unbelief
have you ever had a holographic picture
done of yourself
no not really I I'm
so they're not really of me yeah and
then we're like a formal sitting like
this is Melissa Crenshaw to someone 100
200 years in the future can look back at
um well yeah I guess so I mean the work
I just I just installed a show here on
the island where I live and there are
actually
two images of me that it's quite obvious
that it is of me
they're not portraits of Melissa they're
they have other titles I'm just the
person in there but yeah definitely
somebody could look at that someday and
go and that was the artist
when she was real young
hey yeah I would I would like to see it
happen more
um most of the people who were involved
with the theater photography have
portraits done for future generations to
look back in yeah it would have made a
lot of sense huh you know yeah that kind
of an archive you're involved with
education now at a physics department
what I really am is I'm called a physics
research associate and it was a
wonderful opportunity I had to close my
studio in kit Solano I had to find a new
place for it and burn Simpson who's been
involved in holography for a long long
time arranged for me to move my entire
Optical system the physics department at
cap college and they brought me in as a
research associate so I don't actually
teach although the labs are available
for demonstrations if we need it but
mainly I just have the opportunity to go
there whenever I want and work on um
the kind of research we're working on
now is to hook up the computer animation
and video system you know through the
LCD screen yeah
holographic transfers of that kind of
information so
you're doing some work with your older
pulse masters from the 80s as well I am
yes I missed this show that I just
opened uh has three news well there's
about 10 new images but I've got three
on display and I did a few experimental
Masters when Sid and I shot the pulse
Masters for our work and I'm using those
now which is kind of neat
and I'm doing just open acromats open
aperture acromat transfers which are
real neat they make a black and white
image right just for the film plane and
then of course as you move off the film
plane the whole thing just explodes into
spectral colors no it's sort of a
breaking the rules technique why don't
you let the listeners know about the
show when it opens how long it's running
where it's located in case anyone from
your area happens to log on and they're
listening to this yeah it's just a small
show I live on an island I live on Bowen
Island which is
20 minutes from the mainland where
Vancouver British Columbia is near a
huge City but this is a wonderful little
island it's a lot of artists live here
and we have a local Gallery called Just
The Gallery at Artisan square and that
shows open Friday Saturdays and Sundays
through November 22nd
and I've got some of Sid's work and mine
and I've got some early abstract pieces
I've got some of the z-axis pedestal
abstract pieces from the early 80s and
then I've got three of the new pieces
yeah
school-aged children who may be
listening right now we get a lot of
Educators and students that come onto
the site and listen
what tips would you give them or advice
if they would want to get involved with
photography and especially
that you're a woman working in the field
what would you say to some of the female
student listeners about getting involved
with
technology and art and Technology what
are some of your experiences been in the
past has things changed for you and what
you see happening in the future with it
well I think one of the beautiful things
about holography is that
it opens a door for basically rather
non-technical people which I would have
considered myself before I did
holography it opens the door to artistic
people it opens the door to sort of
non-mathematical people it opens the
door into a world that is used to just
be the domain of physics essentially
yeah and science
and that's a really wonderful thing it
holography provides a bridge between the
creative world of image making and you
know the the world of physics and
Science and to be able to cross that
bridge and go back and forth between
those two worlds is a really wonderful
thing to be able to do and I think that
it's interesting that when I was
um you know younger like 20 years ago
there weren't a lot of women still going
into science and physics and yet this
interesting thing happened in holography
which is that
I would almost
stick my neck out and say that the
majority of Art and art holographers
were women
somehow it was like here was an
opportunity for women to get involved in
the Imaging that involve technology and
they just jumped at the chance and
became excellent I mean some of the best
holographers in the world are women so
go for it
painting
[Laughter]
my daughter has a physics Professor who
I found out was a student that I had a
young lady that I had in one of my
holography classes oh wow back in the
early 80s and she found it so
fascinating that she kept reading books
about it and decided to study Physics
yeah wow that's fantastic that's really
great
mean any anything that opens a door for
you you know and the more doors you have
open for you the more interesting your
life is going to be and holography just
you know it covers so many different
areas
really great that way now you've you've
had your own lab you didn't rent
facilities right no I never had to I
I've always been extremely lucky about
Labs did you work with a sand table
system or did you have the oh yes I
worked with everything
um I started out at the school in
Chicago and we were able to rent for a
dollar an hour Labs on the weekends
which I did then I went I moved to
Seattle and I I I had a Bachelor of
Science degree at that point I wanted to
get my my bachelor of art so I went to a
small State College called Evergreen
State College which just happened to
have
a fabulous holography lab that no one
ever used they had a 50 milliwatt helium
neon laser they had an energy Optics
table I just couldn't believe it just
sitting there huh just sitting there
waiting for me I went to school there
and got my my Bachelor of Arts and then
I ended up teaching holography there for
a year so I basically had that place to
myself
and then Global images wanted to set up
a lab in Vancouver and have an artisan
residence program so they hired me to
design the lab and design the Optics and
to sort of run that program and I did
and when I came here to do my four-month
Artisan residence I never left and
Walter Clark owned Global images and he
ended up going to New York and then I
believe London to run his embossing
business and I ended up owning the lab
wow I know it's just amazing
so then the next thing that happened was
that I thought I was going to have to
close the lab and mothball all the
equipment and everything and then all of
a sudden bring Simpson came to me and
said how would you like to move it to
Cal college so I've been really lucky
that way just really lucky I've always
had equipment so you're basically
working on
not necessarily A Newport table but one
of the production tables now I would
imagine right well it is my old facility
I had a um a homemade table if you like
it with a 7 000 pound concrete and steel
numbered but when we moved into top
college Hollow crafts a very successful
diagramate company here donated a 5 by
10 foot
um NRC table wow so yeah so I mean I've
just been really lucky that way let me
ask you this
he's left in both systems or a number of
different systems I'm speaking
specifically of tables same tables
you've got that concrete and steel table
that you just mentioned and the Newport
if the homemade I'll call them homemade
for lack of a better term table is well
constructed
do you really notice that much of a
difference in the end result absolutely
not there you go folks
my table my Optics table we built for a
thousand dollars at the lab and it
worked like a charm it was beautiful and
I must honestly say that
I cannot I can't tell the table I'm
working on now if I had to go out and
buy it new it would cost about twenty
five thousand dollars I can't possibly
even imagine in a million years that
there's that much of a difference
between the two
I mean you know you just learn I mean
I've built everything I mean I've built
all my Optical holders my components my
frame holders and everything very little
off the shelf ever ends up in my lab
because of money but that's okay you
know
well Melissa do you have any closing
comments or remarks you'd like to say
before we close out the show
I don't know hello to everybody
um and mainly just that you know I think
a lot of us had a bit a bit of a rough
time there when the museum closed and
when the Publications went under and
people stopped collecting but it's great
to know that people are still doing the
work and um you know it's a wonderful
field and it should continue amateur and
hobbyist photography is still fairly
strong oh yes I think so you know and
that's great started yeah exactly
exactly well Melissa thank you very much
for being on the show okay well thank
you very much and don't forget to tune
in sometime during the week as they'll
go up on Sunday night around midnight
and then it will be up for a week okay
um what's the next one